the battle of the coral sea, fought during 4-8 may 1942, was a major 
naval battle in the pacific theater of world war ii between the 
imperial japanese navy (ijn) and naval and air forces from the united 
states and australia. the battle was the first action in which 
aircraft carriers engaged each other, as well as the first in which 
neither side's ships sighted or fired directly upon the other.

in an attempt to strengthen their defensive positioning for their 
empire in the south pacific, japanese forces decided to invade and 
occupy port moresby in new guinea and tulagi in the southeastern 
solomon islands. the plan to accomplish this, called operation mo, 
involved several major units of japan's combined fleet, including two 
fleet carriers and a light carrier to provide air cover for the 
invasion fleets, under the overall command of japanese admiral 
shigeyoshi inoue. the us learned of the japanese plan through signals 
intelligence and sent two united states navy carrier task forces and 
a joint australian-american cruiser force, under the overall command 
of american admiral frank j. fletcher, to oppose the japanese 
offensive.

on 3-4 may, japanese forces successfully invaded and occupied tulagi, 
although several of their supporting warships were surprised and sunk 
or damaged by aircraft from the us fleet carrier yorktown. now aware 
of the presence of us carriers in the area, the japanese fleet 
carriers advanced towards the coral sea with the intention of finding 
and destroying the allied naval forces. beginning on 7 may, the 
carrier forces from the two sides exchanged in airstrikes over two 
consecutive days. the first day, the us sank the japanese light 
carrier shoho, while the japanese sank a us destroyer and heavily 
damaged a fleet oiler (which was later scuttled). the next day, the 
japanese fleet carrier shokaku was heavily damaged, the us fleet 
carrier lexington was critically damaged (and was scuttled as a 
result), and the yorktown was damaged. with both sides having 
suffered heavy losses in aircraft and carriers damaged or sunk, the 
two fleets disengaged and retired from the battle area. because of 
the loss of carrier air cover, inoue recalled the port moresby 
invasion fleet, intending to try again later.
 

